Good morning.
صباح الخير
Let's look for a minute at the greatest icon of all, Leonardo da Vinci.
دعونا ننظر لدقيقة إلى أعظم رمز، ليوناردو دا فينشي
We're all familiar with his fantastic work --
جميعنا يعرف أعماله الرائعة
his drawings, his paintings, his inventions, his writings.
رسوماته، لوحاته، اختراعاته، وكتاباته
But we do not know his face.
ولكننا لا نعرف وجهه
Thousands of books have been written about him,
آلاف الكتب كتبت عنه
but there's controversy, and it remains, about his looks.
ولكن يوجد خلاف، والخلاف مستمر، عن شكله
Even this well-known portrait is not accepted by many art historians.
حتى هذه الثورة المعروفة غير مقبولة عند كثير من مؤرخي الفن
So, what do you think?
فما هو رأيكم؟
Is this the face of Leonardo da Vinci or isn't it?
هل هذا وجه ليوناردو دا فينشي أم لا؟
Let's find out.
دعونا نكتشف
Leonardo was a man that drew everything around him.
ليوناردو رجل رسم كل شيء من حوله
He drew people, anatomy, plants, animals, landscapes, buildings, water, everything.
رسم الناس، النباتات، الحيوانات، المناظر، البنايات، الماء، كل شيء
But no faces?
ولكن الوجوه؟
I find that hard to believe.
أجد ذلك صعب التصديق
His contemporaries made faces, like the ones you see here --
معاصروه رسموا الوجوه، كلتي ترونها هنا
en face or three-quarters.
وجه كامل أو ثلاثة أرباع
So, surely a passionate drawer like Leonardo
لذا من المؤكد أن رساما شغوفا مثل ليوناردو
must have made self-portraits from time to time.
لابد أنه رسم صور شخصية من وقت لآخر
So let's try to find them.
لذا لنحاول العثور عليها
I think that if we were to scan all of his work
أعتقد أننا لو تأملنا كل أعماله
and look for self-portraits, we would find his face looking at us.
ولحثنا عن الصور الشخصية، سنجد وجهه ينظر إلينا
So I looked at all of his drawings, more than 700,
لذا فقد تصفحت جميع أعماله، أكثر من 700
and looked for male portraits.
وبحثت عن صور لذكور
There are about 120, you see them here.
توجد حوالي 120، ترونهم هنا
Which ones of these could be self-portraits?
أيها صورة شخصية؟
Well, for that they have to be done as we just saw, en face or three-quarters.
حسنا، لذلك يجب أن تكون كما رأينا للتو، وجه كامل أو ثلاثة أرباع
So we can eliminate all the profiles.
لذا يمكننا استبعاد جميع الجانبية
It also has to be sufficiently detailed.
كما أنها يجب أن تكون مفصلة
So we can also eliminate the ones that are very vague or very stylized.
لذا يمكننا استبعاد الصور الباهتة أو المنمقة
And we know from his contemporaries
ونعلم من معاصريه
that Leonardo was a very handsome, even beautiful man.
أن ليوناردو كان وسيما جدا، بل وجميل
So we can also eliminate the ugly ones or the caricatures.
لذا يمكننا استبعاد القبحاء أو الهزلية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And look what happens -- only three candidates remain that fit the bill.
وانظروا إلى ما يحدث -- يبقى ثلاث مرشحين فقط تنطبق عليهم المواصفات
And here they are.
وها هم
Yes, indeed, the old man is there,
وبالفعل، الرجل العجوز هنا
as is this famous pen drawing of the Homo Vitruvianus.
كما هي الرسمة المشهورة هومو فيدروفيانس
And lastly, the only portrait of a male that Leonardo painted, "The Musician."
وأخيرا، اللوحة الوحيدة التي رسمها ليوناردو لرجل "المسيقار"ـ
Before we go into these faces,
قبل أن نتعمق في هذه الوجوه
I should explain why I have some right to talk about them.
على أن أشرح عن أحقيتي في التحدث عنهم
I've made more than 1,100 portraits myself
لقد رسمت أكثر من 1,100 صور
for newspapers, over the course of 300 -- 30 years, sorry, 30 years only.
للصحف، على مر 300 -- 30 عام، آسف 30 عام فقط
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But there are 1,100, and very few artists have drawn so many faces.
ولكن هناك 1,100، والقليل جدا من الفنانين قاموا برسم هذا العدد من الوجوه
So I know a little about drawing and analyzing faces.
لذا فأنا أعرف القليل عن رسم وتحليل الوجوه
OK, now let's look at these three portraits.
حسنا، دعونا ننظر إلى هذه الصور الثلاث
And hold onto your seats, because if we zoom in on those faces,
تمسكوا بمقاعدكم، لأننا إذا قربنا النظر على هذه الوجوه
remark how they have the same broad forehead, the horizontal eyebrows,
لاحظوا أن جميعها لها نفس الجبهة العريضة، والحواجب الأفقية
the long nose, the curved lips and the small, well-developed chin.
الأنف الطويل، الشفاه المنحنية، والذقن الصغيرة
I couldn't believe my eyes when I first saw that.
لم أصدق عيني حين رأيت ذلك لأول مرة
There is no reason why these portraits should look alike.
لا يوجد أي سبب لتتشابه هذه الصور
All we did was look for portraits that had the characteristics of a self-portrait,
كل ما قمنا به هو البحث عن صور لديها خصائص الصور الشخصية
and look, they are very similar.
وانظروا، إنهم متشابهين جدا
Now, are they made in the right order?
الآن، هل رسمت بالترتيب الصحيح؟
The young man should be made first.
الشاب يجب أن يأتي أولا
And as you see here from the years that they were created,
وكما ترون هنا من سنوات الرسم
it is indeed the case.
إنها بالفعل كذلك
They are made in the right order.
رسمت بالترتيب الصحيح
What was the age of Leonardo at the time? Does that fit?
ما هو عمر ليوناردو وقتها؟ هل ينطبق ذلك؟
Yes, it does. He was 33, 38 and 63 when these were made.
نعم. كان 33، 38 و 63 حين رسمت هذه
So we have three pictures, potentially of the same person
إذا لدينا ثلاث صور، محتملة لنفس الشخص
of the same age as Leonardo at the time.
في نفس عمر ليوناردو وقتها
But how do we know it's him, and not someone else?
ولكن هل نعرف أنه هو، وليس شخصا آخر؟
Well, we need a reference.
حسنان، نحتاج إلى مرجع
And here's the only picture of Leonardo that's widely accepted.
وهذه هي الصورة الوحيدة المقبولة لليوناردو
It's a statue made by Verrocchio, of David,
إنها تمثال صنعه فيروكيو، من ديفيد
for which Leonardo posed as a boy of 15.
حيث وقف ليوناردو كصبي ذا 15
And if we now compare the face of the statue,
والآن إذا قارنا وجه التمثال
with the face of the musician, you see the very same features again.
مع الموسيقار، ترون الملامح نفسها مجددا
The statue is the reference, and it connects the identity of Leonardo
التمثال هو المرجع، وهي تربط هوية ليوناردو
to those three faces.
لهذه الوجوه الثلاث
Ladies and gentlemen, this story has not yet been published.
سيداتي وسادتي، هذه القصة لم تنشر بعد
It's only proper that you here at TED hear and see it first.
إنه من اللائق أن تسمعوا هنا في تيد وترو هذا أولا
The icon of icons finally has a face.
رمز الرموز أخيرا له وجه
Here he is: Leonardo da Vinci.
هذا هو -- ليوناردو دا فينشي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)